A Guide to the Papers of Dr. James Carmichael 1816-1834
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Dr. James Carmichael 1816-1834
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11373
ca. 675 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1 linear foot)
This collection consists of the correspondence, 1819-1830, 1834, and undated, and day book, 1816-1817, of Dr. James Carmichael (1771-1831) and his son, Edward Carmichael, of Fredericksburg, Virginia, ca. 675 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1 linear foot), who emigrated from Scotland in the 1780s to practice medicine in the Fredericksburg area. Dr. James Carmichael was one of the physicians involved in treating yellow fever, which was epidemic in 1803 in the Fredericksburg area, and began a family of physicians continuing to the present.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Jerry Showalter, Bookseller, Ivy, Virginia, on January 30, 1998.
Scope and Content Information
The correspondence discusses medical treatment, the prescription of medicine, and urgent requests for visits from the physician, from the perspective of the patient, family, and slave owner. There are no letters from Dr. Carmichael to his patients. The collection also contains a few accounts and receipts scattered among the letters, some of which also deal with the purchase of reference books and medical supplies (1820 May 6, 29, June 7; 1821 Dec 10; 1822 Apr 17, 18, Sep 27; 1823 Mar 19, Aug 29, Oct 1, 31; 1824 Apr 8, 15, May 27, Sep 30, Oct 19, 22, Nov 18; 1825 Apr 8, 25, May 16, Aug 19; 1827 Jun 7, Dec 7; 1828 Apr 7, May 6).
At least seventy-five different area families are represented in this collection and some of the correspondents include: Mann Page, Hugh Mercer (n.d.), Burr Harrison, Fontaine Maury, Bushrod Washington, St. Ledger Landon Carter (1823 Oct 23; 1826 Oct 8, n.d.), James Barbour (n.d.) and Edmund Berkeley. Letters of special interest include one from Robert Carter from Sabine Hall, March 26, 1828, and from hotel keeper, J[ohn?] Gray, at the University of Virginia, March 15, 1825.
Contents List
- Day Book of Dr. James Carmichael 1816-1817 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Dr. James Carmichael 1819-1830, 1834, n.d., 10 folders (Box 1-2)
  Many of the letters to him pertain to the medical treatment of local slaves and a list of all letters discussing the health of slaves or possible slaves follows:
  - Letter 1819 Dec 23 (Box 1)
    swollen knee
  - Letter 1820 Jan 3 (Box 1)
    Scipio need for a truss (Pratt family)
  - Letter 1820 Jan 14 & 23 (Box 1)
    unspecified
  - Letter 1820 Jan 27 (Box 1)
    mumps
  - Letter 1820 Feb 11 (Box 1)
    tooth extraction for Ned (Jones family)
  - Letter 1820 Feb 16 (Box 1)
    child with worms
  - Letter 1820 Mar 27 (Box 1)
    slave purged and bled, inquires about the need for a blister treatment
  - Letter 1820 Mar 28, 29 (Box 1)
    woman bleeding from the nose
  - Letter 1820 Jul 18 (Box 1)
    man in considerable pain
  - Letter 1820 Sep 10 (Box 1)
    several of the people are very sick
  - Letter 1820 Oct 3 (Box 1)
    Israel has the pox (Hooe family)
  - Letter 1820 Oct 10 (Box 1)
  - Letter 1820 Oct 26 (Box 1)
    headache and fever
  - Letter 1821 Jan 6 (Box 1)
    Woman sick at Clark's
  - Letter 1821 Apr 5 (Box 1)
    infection in the eyes of two slave boys
  - Letter 1821 Apr 8 (Box 1)
    George's wife is sick (Long family)
  - Letter 1821 Apr 27 (Box 1)
    Patty's sick child with worms or cold (Jones)
  - Letter 1821 Apr 25 (Box 1)
    Judy's sick child with ear infection or whooping cough, "as all our black children have it" (Jones family)
  - Letter 1820 May 10; 1822 Jul 30 (Box 1)
    Slave of Bernard's estate sick
  - Letter 1821 May 15 (Box 1)
    Robin has pain in his side (Lipscomb)
  - Letter 1821 May 15 (Box 1)
  - Letter 1821 May 19 (Box 1)
    Anthony has permit to visit doctor (Selden)
  - Letter 1821 Aug 15 (Box 1)
    [Brass?] very ill with fever (Stanard)
  - Letter 1821 Aug 19, 31 (Box 1)
    Delphia has fever and other symptoms (Herndon)
  - Letter 1821 Sep 22 (Box 1)
    slave man ill with fever and pain in head & neck
  - Letter 1821 Sep 29 (Box 1)
    woman Jenny taken with a bleeding (Strachan)
  - Letter 1821 Oct 1 (Box 1)
    James ill with fever (Jones family)
  - Letter 1821 Dec 4 (Box 1)
    Nelson sent for examination (Jones family)
  - Letter 1822 Jan 3 (Box 1)
    Edmond's elbow may be out of place (Alsop family)
  - Letter 1822 Jan 22 (Box 1)
    [Hill?] has "the polite disorder" (Jones family)
  - Letter 1822 Apr 4 (Box 1)
    a slave woman in labor called a "Calcutta case"
  - Letter 1822 Jul 13 (Box 1)
    Reuben has a "strong complaint" (Jones family)
  - Letter 1822 Aug 20 (Box 1)
    boy with pain in left side
  - Letter 1823 Feb 18 (Box 1)
    young slave boy has a very bad eye (Jackson family)
  - Letter 1823 Mar 3 (Box 1)
    young woman with ulcerated leg (Mitchell family)
  - Letter 1823 Apr 9, May 11 young slave woman with a swollen knee (Battaile family) (Box 1)
  - Letter 1823 May 1 (Box 1)
    five year old boy with worms and headache (Stanard family)
  - Letter 1823 May 9 (Box 1)
    male slave suffering derangement (Morson family)
  - Letter 1823 May 30 (Box 1)
    slave woman Judy wishes to be bled (Jones estate)
  - Letter 1823 Jun 4 (Box 1)
    slave boy with high fever and headache (Stanard family)
  - Letter 1823 Jul 12 (Box 1)
    slave girl with boils (Jones family)
  - Letter 1823 Jul 25 (Box 1)
    slave girl with high fever and headache (Jackson)
  - Letter 1823 Sep 6 (Box 1)
    slave boy very sick with poison oak (Seddon family)
  - Letter 1823 Sep 6 (Box 1)
    Uncle's slave is sick
  - Letter 1823 Sep 20 (Box 1)
    arrangements to bring two slaves home
  - Letter 1824 Feb 6 (Box 1)
    slave man with a rupture
  - Letter 1824 Feb 25 (Box 1)
    slave very ill
  - Letter 1824 Apr 26 (Box 1)
    pain in slave woman's side
  - Letter 1824 Jun 10 (Box 1)
    male slave needs a truss
  - Letter 1824 Sep 3 (Box 1)
    male slave with "the gravel"
  - Letter 1824 Sep 29 (Box 1)
    female slave unable to deliver her child
  - Letter 1824 Dec 17 (Box 1)
    female slave with stomach, chest and throat pain
  - Letter 1825 Jan 19 (Box 2)
  - Letter 1825 Jan 25 (Box 2)
    female slave with headache and backache
  - Letter 1825 May 20 (Box 2)
    a slave boy is very ill
  - Letter 1825 Jul 14 (Box 2)
    Gerard is ill (Forbes family)
  - Letter 1825 Sep 16 (Box 2)
    Caroline, 34 years old, suffering from asthma (Hooe family)
  - Letter 1825 Sep 26 (Box 2)
    death of a slave girl
  - Letter 1825 Dec 11 (Box 2)
    male slave with fistula
  - Letter 1826 Jan 28 (Box 2)
    male slave dangerously ill
  - Letter 1826 May 30 (Box 2)
    female slave with the thrush
  - Letter 1826 Aug 2 (Box 2)
    sends Rachel with her child (Strothers family)
  - Letter 1826 Aug 10, 16 (Box 2)
    slave child with worms
  - Letter 1826 Oct 8 (Box 2)
    slave woman very ill
  - Letter 1826 Oct 28 (Box 2)
    male slave Frank still ill (Stanard family)
  - Letter 1827 Jan 10, 13 (Box 2)
    slave woman [Harrie?] with severe sore throat
  - Letter 1827 Feb 16 (Box 2)
    Ned has frostbitten fingers (Clark)
  - Letter 1827 Mar 13 (Box 2)
    slave boy with infected teeth
  - Letter 1827 Mar 18 (Box 2)
    slave woman with obstruction
  - Letter 1827 Apr 27 (Box 2)
    little boy with ague
  - Letter 1827 Jun 4 (Box 2)
    child Isaac with eye inflammation
  - Letter 1827 Jul 19 (Box 2)
    Patsy much worse (Gordon family)
  - Letter 1827 Aug 9 (Box 2)
    slave boy grows worse
  - Letter 1827 Sep 1 (Box 2)
    Nelly will describe her complaint (Taliaferro family)
  - Letter 1827 Oct 2 (Box 2)
    slave girl very ill
  - Letter 1827 Nov 16 (Box 2)
    slave woman with fever and headache
  - Letter 1828 Jan 15 (Box 2)
    slave girl with eye inflammation
  - Letter 1828 Mar 15 (Box 2)
    slave girl sent for examination
  - Letter 1828 Jun 25 (Box 2)
    Matilda and thumb problem (Maury family)
  - Letter 1828 Jul 16 (Box 2)
    sick servant
  - Letter 1828 Aug 4 (Box 2)
    a one year old child with bowel trouble
  - Letter 1829 Mar 15 (Box 2)
    male slave unwell
  - Letter 1829 Apr 7 (Box 2)
    male slave James needs treatment